A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Series AA FA336
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Series AA
1858-1957, n.d. 1920-1948
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller family
FA336
42 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé.
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in eight subseries:
Subseries 1 - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Correspondence Subseries 2 - Personal Papers Subseries 3 - Art Collections Subseries 4 - Philanthropy Files Subseries 5 - Aldrich/Greene Family Papers Subseries 6 - Death of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Subseries 7 - Chase Biography Files Subseries 8 - Family Correspondence
Scope and Contents note
Abby Greene Aldrich Rockefeller was born in Providence, Rhode Island on October 26, 1874, the fourth child of Abby Pearce Chapman (1845-1917) and Nelson Wilmarth Aldrich (1841-1915). Nelson Aldrich rose from the position of bookkeeper in a wholesale grocery firm to become a member of the State House of Representatives; he was Speaker of the House from 1876 to 1877. From 1881 to 1911, he served as United States Senator from Rhode Island. In 1899, he was elevated to the chairmanship of the Senate Finance Committee, an appointment he held until his retirement in 1911. The family maintained homes in Providence, Warwick Neck, and Washington.
Abby Rockefeller received her early education from Quaker governesses. At seventeen, she began attending Miss Abbott's School for Young Ladies in Providence, where her courses included English composition and literature, French, German, art history and ancient history, gymnastics, and dancing. She graduated in 1893 and made her debut the following November. On June 30, 1894, she sailed for Liverpool, inaugurating a lifetime of European travel. The aesthetic education she received abroad, fostered initially by her father, helped to form her judgment as an art collector. Her first four-month sojourn included stays in England, Belgium, the Netherlands, Germany, Austria, Switzerland, Italy, and France.
In the fall of 1894 at the Providence home of a classmate, Abby met John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960), son of the founder of Standard Oil Company, who was then a sophomore at Brown University. After a lengthy courtship, they married on October 9, 1901. They had six children: Abby (1903-1976), John Davison, 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson Aldrich (1908-1979), Laurance Spelman (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915- ). The Rockefellers lived at No. 10 W. 54th Street from 1901 to 1938, when they moved to an apartment at 740 Park Avenue. They had homes at Pocantico Hills, New York; Seal Harbor, Maine; and Williamsburg, Virginia, and were active members of these communities.
When the United States entered World War I, Mrs. Rockefeller's charitable and philanthropic activities began in earnest. From 1917 to 1919, Mrs. Rockefeller served as Chairman of Auxiliary 336 of the American Red Cross, completely financing its work. Quarters at No. 4 W. 54th Street were dedicated to preparing thousands of "comfort bags" for shipment through the YWCA-YMCA Navy League and Army and Navy Debarkation hospitals to the fighting fronts in Russia, Italy, and France.
In 1917, Mrs. Rockefeller became chairman of the newly created Housing Committee of the War Work Council of the National Board of the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA). Her report, "Suggestions for Housing Women War Workers" (1918), prompted the federal government to enact building standards for the housing of women at industrial sites, based on the experience of 200 YWCA boarding houses. Mrs. Rockefeller's interest in securing quality housing for working people led her in 1917 to chair the Grace Dodge Hotel Committee of the YWCA. Overcrowded housing conditions in Washington, D.C., resulting from the influx of women war workers, had necessitated immediate relief. The Grace Dodge Hotel for women opened in 1921. Mrs. Rockefeller closely monitored the hotel's design and operation until 1937. She was one of the earliest champions of hotels for women.
In 1919, Mrs. Rockefeller became interested in the living conditions of the employees of the Bayway Refinery of Standard Oil, located in the Bayway section of Elizabeth, New Jersey. John D. Rockefeller purchased six lots of land and deeded them to Mrs. Rockefeller for the construction of Bayway Cottage, a model workers' home. In 1928, the cottage was expanded and renamed Bayway Community House; the House was incorporated in 1937 as the Bayway Community Center. By 1943, some 4,000 families were using the Center and its clinics, gyms, nursery schools, bowling alleys, and meeting rooms. Over a twenty-year period, Mrs. Rockefeller's contributions amounted to $200,000.
With the founding of the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) in May 1929, the scope of Abby Rockefeller's philanthropy widened dramatically. Her aesthetic insight and administrative and personal skills now found their fullest application, and she gained a permanent home for her personal collection of modern art.
Although the idea of establishing a museum dedicated to fostering modern art had been floating about since the celebrated Armory Show of 1913, it was not until Abby Rockefeller began to solicit the advice of her own friends during the winter of 1928-1929 that the idea moved towards realization. Conversations with Lillie P. Bliss, patroness of the painter Arthur B. Davies, and Mary Quinn Sullivan, a collector, led to a meeting in May 1929 at which the three women invited A. Conger Goodyear to chair a museum organizing committee. In July, the young Alfred H. Barr, Jr. was appointed director. A seven-member Board of Trustees was elected in October 1929 and included Abby Rockefeller, Lillie Bliss, Mary Quinn Sullivan, A. Conger Goodyear, Frank Crowninshield (editor of Vanity Fair magazine), Mrs. W. Murray Crane (a supporter of the experimental Dalton School), and Paul J. Sachs (Professor of Fine Arts at Harvard).
Mrs. Rockefeller held several positions at the Museum from 1929 to 1945. From 1929 to 1934, she served as museum Treasurer. From 1934 to 1936, and again from January to May 1939, she held the post of First Vice President. During the war years, from December 1941 until November 1945, she served as First Vice Chairman. Mrs. Rockefeller was a member of several committees of the Board of Trustees. She served on the Executive Committee (1930-1945), chairing that committee in 1936. She was a member of the Fine Art Committee from 1930 to 1934 and of the Exhibitions Committee from 1930 to 1939. She promoted the establishment in 1935 of a Film Library. With Stephen C. Clark and Kenneth Chorley, she organized the War Veterans' Art Center in 1944, which offered art classes to disabled veterans until 1948.
Mrs. Rockefeller's first gift to the new museum was an oil by Bernard Karfiol. Her largest gift, and the largest since the 1934 Bliss bequest, came in 1935 with her presentation of 181 paintings and drawings. This represented practically her entire collection of modern art, gathered over the preceding ten years, and comprised the work of seventy-one American and foreign artists. In 1936, Mrs. Rockefeller gave the museum its first formal purchase funds; these were augmented in 1938 by another gift and increased by half by Nelson A. Rockefeller in his mother's name. The 1938 fund, named the Mrs. John D. Rockefeller Jr. Purchase Fund, was unrestricted. In 1949, the Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Print Room opened at MoMA, housing Abby's gift of sixteen hundred prints, which had been given nine years earlier.
In addition to her gifts to the Museum of Modern Art, Abby Rockefeller gave substantially to other museums, including the Metropolitan Museum of Art and The Cloisters, which received much of her collection of sculpture and decorative arts; the Rhode Island School of Design, which received her collection of Japanese prints; and the Ludwell-Paradise House at Colonial Williamsburg, which in 1939 received her entire collection of American folk art, collected since 1931.
Mrs. Rockefeller's numerous church activities included service as Vice President of the Women's Bible Class at the 5th Avenue Baptist Church and Honorary Vice President of the Women's Society of Riverside Church. She was a member of the Building Committee of International House, Chairman of the Decorating Committee and one of its trustees. She was a charter member of the Cosmopolitan Club and a member of the Colony Club, the Women's City Club, the National Society of Colonial Dames, the Women's National Republican Club, the Faculty Club of Harvard University, the Mayflower Descendants, and the Garden Club of America, among others.
Abby Rockefeller died April 5, 1948 at her New York apartment. The Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Papers document the life and philanthropic activities of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Medical research; Medical education; New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Juvenile delinquency; International relations -- United States; Medical care; Maternal health services; International economic relations; International cooperation; International relations; International education; Charities -- Investments; Charities; Civic improvement; Child welfare; Prohibition; Public health; Public health administration; Public policy; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Performing arts; Folk art; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Health insurance; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Public welfare; Religion; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Travel; United States; Urban policy; Urban renewal; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Business enterprises, Foreign; Capital investments; Arts; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Business; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Economic development; Art; Economics; Economic policy; Education -- United States; Education; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Philanthropy; World War II; World War I; Philanthropy -- United States
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Papers - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Correspondence, 1882-1957 1920-1948; AA.1; 9 Document Box(es)
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 1, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Correspondence, is arranged in two sections, Personal and Professional. Within Personal Correspondence, letters are arranged in two runs: Named and Subject correspondence. Named correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence. Within each section and run, letters have been filed alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's personal and professional correspondence (1882-1957) is located in Subseries 1, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Correspondence. Major correspondents include Abby's sister, Lucy Truman Aldrich, with whom Abby corresponded at length for thirty years; siblings Nelson, Edward, Stuart, William, Richard, Winthrop, and Elsie; and her six children: Abby (Babs), John Davison 3rd, Nelson, Laurance, Winthrop, and David. The correspondence between Abby and David Rockefeller remains closed. For what survives of Abby's letters to John D. Rockefeller, Jr., consult the John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Papers in Record Group 2, Series Z of the Rockefeller Family Archives.
  Abby's correspondence with her brothers (Elsie Aldrich is not a primary correspondent) fills six folders. Letters reveal the friendly rapport and mutual respect that existed between the Aldrich siblings. They also provide information on Abby's occasional anonymous donations to projects in Boston and Providence for which her brothers sought her support. William, who was an architect in Boston, shared Abby's aesthetic interests and often recommended to her the purchase of paintings and furniture.
  Among her children, Abby wrote most frequently to Winthrop Rockefeller, especially during the years of his army service (1941-1945) in World War II. Letters (1916-1948) from Babs to her mother include passionate appeals to return home from summer camp and accounts of sightseeing in Europe in 1920-1921 with her aunt, Lucy Truman Aldrich.
  There are thirteen letters (1887-1909, n.d.) to Abby from her mother, Abby Pearce Chapman Aldrich. In a letter dated 8 March 1897, Mrs. Aldrich advises against a visit to New York, in case "Mamma Rockaffller... think you are chasing her son." Abby's letters to her mother are located in Subseries 5. There are thirteen letters (1887-1914, n.d.) to Abby from her father, Nelson W. Aldrich. Some are brief notes enclosed with checks; others display a rare sensitivity. Writing in the 1890s to his now teen-age daughter, the Senator acknowledges impending changes: "Your letter reminds me that very soon I shall not be able to deal with you as a little girl to be disposed of without consultation but that you will have to be treated with as a young lady, with wants and demands."
  Other correspondents include Italianist Bernard Berenson, writing in 1927 from I Tatti; archaeologist James Henry Breasted, describing the recently unearthed tomb of King Tutankhamen; landscape architect Beatrice Ferrand, and painters Henri Matisse (two letters, 1932, 1933), Georgia O'Keefe, Walter Pach, and Peter Blume. Letters (1929-1937) from Eustache de Lorey of the Institut Français d'Archéologie et d'Art Musulmans discuss recent exhibitions, various pieces of Persian and Indian art, and modern pictures de Lorey envisioned for the Museum of Modern Art.
  Also housed in Subseries 1 are twenty-four folders of Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) correspondence (1929-1945, 1947). This is largely Abby's incoming correspondence from museum staff relating to exhibitions and loans, personnel and financial matters, the War Veterans' Art Center, and modern movement in art. Major correspondents include Abby's financial adviser Arthur W. Packard, MoMA Director Alfred Barr, A. Conger Goodyear (President of MoMA), Monroe Wheeler (Director of Exhibitions and Publications), Stephen C. Clark (Chairman of the Board), Frances Hawkins (Secretary), James Thrall Soby (Director of Paintings and Sculpture), and John E. Abbott (Executive Vice President). Stephen Clark's moving tribute to Abby's moral leadership of the museum during the war years is housed in Subseries 7, Chase Biography Files, in folder 339.
  The General Office File (1909-1955), a correspondence file maintained by John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s office staff, contains information on Mrs. Rockefeller's charitable activities.
  Related Archival Materials note
  For Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's correspondence regarding her philanthropic work, see Subseries 4 - Philanthropy Files.
  For Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's correspondence to her mother Abby Pearce Chapman Aldrich, and other Aldrich and Greene family correspondence, see Subseries 5 - Aldrich/Greene Family Papers.
  For Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's correspondence to John D. Rockefeller, Jr., see the Rockefeller Family Archives, Record Group 2 - Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller, Series Z - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal Papers.
  - (Empty Folder) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (A) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Abby Pearce Chapman, 1887, 1892, 1894, 1897, 1905-1906, 1909, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman (Uncalendared), 1889, 1893, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Calendar to the Letters of Lucy Truman Aldrich to Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, ca. 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    See also Folders 6-14, 85-86.
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1919, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1924-1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1928, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Lucy Truman, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich, Nelson Wilmarth, 1881, 1887-1888, 1890-1891, 1893, 1914, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich Brothers (Edward, Richard, William, Winthrop), 1894, 1918-1921 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich Brothers (Edward, Richard, William, Winthrop), 1922-1925 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich Brothers (Edward, Richard, William, Winthrop), 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich Brothers (Edward, Richard, William, Winthrop), 1928-1930 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich Brothers (Edward, Richard, William, Winthrop), 1931-1936 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Aldrich Brothers (Edward, Richard, William, Winthrop), 1937-1939, 1941-1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (B) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Breasted, James Henry, 1923, 1925-1928, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (Ca) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (Ch-Cu) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Crawford, Margaret, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (D) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - de Lorey, Eustache, 1929-1937, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (E) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (F) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (G) (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Goddard, Madeleine, 1892, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Greene, Lucy E., 1887-1888, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (H) (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - Hooker, Blanchette Ferry, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (I-J) (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (K) (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - King, W. Mackenzie, 1915, 1919-1920, 1922, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (L) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Personal Correspondence - Named - General (M) (Box 3, Folder 40)